Amateur Hour Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Amateur Hour Collection1934-1948
ML31.A4
Bowes, Edward, Major, 1874-1946
circa 8500 items 20 boxes 9 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Primarily over 7000 applications from contestants who appeared on the Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour radio program between 1934 and 1948. A small percentage of the administrative papers dating from the late 1940s and 1950s, as well as materials relating to the Mexican version of the program, La hora internacional del aficionado, are also included. Filed with the contestant applications are letters of introduction, reference letters, and other documents sent by prospective contestants. Applications from conventional performers such as musicians, dancers, singers, and impersonators are the most numerous, but also included are applications from novelty acts such as a human piccolo, a group of hand-standing singers, and a group who played harmonicas with fire extinguishers. Of particular interest are applications from various performers, now well-known, including Teresa Brewer, Stubby Kaye, Robert Merrill, Beverly Sills, and Frank Sinatra. Photographs from the 1940s and 1950s provide a visual record of the show, while correspondence to and from program staff members recount some of the program's business transactions. Scripts, promotional material, and advertising and sponsor documents also are part of the collection.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bowes, Edward, Major, 1874-1946.; Brewer, Teresa.; Kaye, Stubby.; Mack, Ted.; Merrill, Robert, 1917-2004.; Sills, Beverly.; Sinatra, Frank, 1915-1998.
Subjects
Talent shows--United States.
Titles
Major Bowes' original amateur hour collection, 1934-1948; Original amateur hour collection, 1934-1948; Original amateur hour--Sources.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Deposit, Joseph Brown 1970.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The Library of Congress, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division has in its custody both the Original Amateur Hour radio broadcasts dating from 1935 to 1944 and the television recordings of the show from 1948 to 1968.
Access and Restrictions
The Amateur Hour Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Agency Sketch
Date Event
April 1934 First radio broadcast of Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour on WHN, New York
1935 William Edward Maguiness (stage name Ted Mack) joins Bowes as emcee and talent scout
March 24, 1935 Coast to coast broadcast on NBC radio with Chase & Sanborn as sponsor
June 1935 Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour is named the most listened to radio program in the United States
Sept. 8, 1935 The Hoboken Four, featuring Frank Sinatra, performs on the Original Amateur Hour program
Sept. 17, 1936 Original Amateur Hour moves to CBS radio, with Chrysler Corporation as sponsor
1944 Major Bowes retires for health reasons
1945 Radio broadcast of Original Amateur Hour is suspended
June 13, 1946 Major Bowes dies
Jan. 14, 1948 Original Amateur Hour is revived on television by Dumont Studios, with Ted Mack as emcee
Oct. 29, 1948 P. Lorillard Company becomes a sponsor
Oct. 4, 1949 First national television broadcast of Original Amateur Hour, on NBC
1952 Final radio broadcast
April 25, 1953 Pet Milk becomes a sponsor
Oct. 30, 1955 Television program broadcasts on ABC
Jan. 19, 1957 La Hora Internacional del Aficionado, Mexican version of program, broadcasts
July 1, 1957 Program returns to NBC television
May 1, 1959 Program broadcasts on CBS
March 7, 1960 Program returns to ABC
Oct. 2, 1960 Programs returns to CBS
Sept. 20, 1970 Final broadcast
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Amateur Hour Collection consist primarily of over 7,000 applications from contestants who appeared on the Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour radio program between 1934 and 1948. The remainder of the materials in the collection are administrative papers dating from the late 1940s and 1950s. Although these materials are only a small percentage of the admistrative papers of the organization, they are worthy of note in that they provide some insight into the way in which the Original Amateur Hour program was run. Materials relating to the Mexican version of the program, La Hora Internacional del Aficionado, are also included.
The Amateur Hour collection is represented by twelve series. The first series is CONTESTANTS consists primarily of over 7,000 applications from contestants who appeared on the Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour radio program between 1934 and 1948. This series is divided into three subseries: Contestant applications; Contestant biographical sketches; Lists of performers.
Filed with the contestant applications are letters of introduction, reference letters, and other documents sent by prospective contestants. Both the "type of entertainment" and "details of interest" responses on the applications provide an overview of the broad range of amateur performance genres of the period. Applications from conventional performers such as musicians, dancers, singers, and impersonators are the most numerous, but also included are applications from novelty acts such as a human piccolo, a group of hand-standing singers, and a group who played harmonicas with fire extinguishers. Of particular interest are applications from various performers, now well-known, who "got their break" on the show, including Teresa Brewer, Stubby Kaye, Robert Merrill, Beverly Sills, and Frank Sinatra.
The second series is PHOTOGRAPHS consisting of photo prints (B&W) of various sizes and arranged by subject. An interesting collection of photographs from the 1940s and 1950s provides a visual record of the show.
The third series is CORRESPONDENCE consists of correspondence to and from program staff members Lou Goldberg, Daniel Manjarrez, and Harry McWilliams recounts some of the program's business transactions and is arranged by subject.
The other nine series consist of administration and operations materials. The general program information, advertising packages, and ratings information are included with Advertising/Sponsor papers. Scripts are housed with the Production materials.
Organization of the Amateur Hour Collection
The Amateur Hour Collection is organized in 12 series:
Contestants
Photographs
Correspondence
Advertising/sponsor materials
Promotional materials
Production materials
Financial papers
Legal papers
Printed programs of performances
Clippings
Awards
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010563506
Container List
- Contestants (Box-folder 1/1-16/6)
  Applications and other related materials of contestants for the Amateur Hour. The majority of which pretain specifically to the Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour radio program between 1934 and 1948.
  Arrangement is in three subseries: Contestant applications; Contestant biographical sketches; Lists of Performers.
  - Contestant applications, related correspondence and documents (Box 1-15)
    Applications from contestants who appeared on the Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour radio program between 1934 and 1948.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by name
    - Aalrud to Alvi (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Amato to Astroff (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Atanasoff to Banks (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Barad to Beloff (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Benak to Bishop (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Bjornie to Bombara (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Bon Bons to Bauner (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Breen to Brydof (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Buchannan to Capwell (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Cardonna to Caye (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Clancy to Connie (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Connors to Cross (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Crowell to Davis (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Davy to Dexter (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Diamond to Dottie and Bobbie (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Dougherty to Dynamic Harmonica Four (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Eagle to Ely (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Emerick to Farrow (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Fasany to Fiore (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Five Aces to Flatbush Floogies (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Fleer to Foster (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Four Amateur Rogues to Fourtan (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Fox to Fyfe (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Gaderick to Gaynor (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Geankoplis to Giusti (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Goerger to Grazzini (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Great Lakes Swing Sextet to Gypsy Quartet (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Hackman to Harmony Four (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Harold to Hechl (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Hedling to Hjerpe (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Hoag to Hopkinson (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Horlbogen to Hylselop (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Idaho Ranch Boys to Jive'n Five (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Joan and Ernie to Juvinall (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Kaaren to Keenan (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Keister to Kiwanis Quartette of Yonkers (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Klaff to Kwan (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Laborde to Lazzesi (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Leah to Leslie (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Leuname to Logue (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Lohr to Lyric Male Quartet (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Maas to M[a]cVeigh (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Macchiaverna to Mansan (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Maranville to Maryella (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Mäsch to Melodie (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Melodious Harmonica Trio to Mike and Bill (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Miki to Mistichelli (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Mitchel to Morris, D. (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Morris, M. to Myers (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Nadel to Nogueira (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Nona to O'Neil, R. (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Ooms to Pagin (Box-folder 11/1)
    - Pagliarini to Payne (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Peace and Pizzuto (Box-folder 11/3)
    - Plantation Four to Puzelli (Box-folder 11/4)
    - Quantico Marine Quartet to Rezits (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Rhodes to Robbins, R. (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Robbins, S. to Rondeau (Box-folder 12/2)
    - Roosa to Rozman (Box-folder 12/3)
    - Rubenstein, L. to Sanders (Box-folder 12/4)
    - Sandherr to Scott (Box-folder 12/5)
    - Seabee Quartet to Shiff (Box-folder 13/1)
    - Shilton to Six Janitors (Box-folder 13/2)
    - Six Jars of Jam to Southwick (Box-folder 13/3)
    - Spadafora to Stewart (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Stock to Swing Sisters Trio (Box-folder 13/5)
    - Swingers of Harmony to Texas Wanderers (Box-folder 13/6)
    - Thatcher to Three Coxswains (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Three Davis Brothers to Three Mouth Organ Kings (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Three Niblicks to Towle (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Tracy to Tyler (Box-folder 14/4)
    - Watcher and Freeman to Weal (Box-folder 14/5)
    - Wetherson to Westward Ho! (Box-folder 14/6)
    - Uccellini to Vuylsteke (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Whalen to Williams, L. (Box-folder 15/2)
    - Williams, M. to Wittig (Box-folder 15/3)
    - Wobnick to Wyoming Range Buddies (Box-folder 15/4)
    - Yaffe to Zyne (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Contestants' biographical sketches (Box-folder 16/1-2)
    Brief biographical sketches of contestants who appeared on the Major Bowes' Original Amateur Hour radio program between 1934 and 1948.
    Arranged alphabetical order by name
    - All Girl Swing Band to One Man Band (Box-folder 16/1)
    - Kathleen Ray to Frances White (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Lists of performers (Box-folder 16/3-5)
    Typescript lists of performers from the Amateur Hour.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by nationality
    - American (Box-folder 16/3)
    - Irish (Box-folder 16/4)
    - Mexican (Box-folder 16/5)
- Photographs (Box-folder 16/6-33)
  Photo prints (B&W) of various sizes.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject
  - Cowboy Acts (Box-folder 16/6)
  - Dancers: Adult, male (Box-folder 16/7)
  - Dancers: Adult, female (Box-folder 16/8)
  - Dancers: Child, female (Box-folder 16/9)
  - Partners, Adult (Box-folder 16/10)
  - Partners, Child (Box-folder 16/11)
  - Impersonators (Box-folder 16/12)
  - Instrumentalists:
    - Accordion players (Box-folder 16/13)
    - Bands (Box-folder 16/14)
    - Bellringers (Box-folder 16/15)
    - Guitar players (Box-folder 16/16)
    - Harmonica players (Box-folder 16/17)
    - Piano players (Box-folder 16/18)
    - Trumpet players (Box-folder 16/19)
    - Xylophone players (Box-folder 16/20)
  - Rollerskaters (Box-folder 16/21)
  - Singers: Adult, male (Box-folder 16/22)
  - Singers: Adult, female (Box-folder 16/23)
  - Singers: Child, male (Box-folder 16/24)
  - Singers: Child, female (Box-folder 16/25)
  - Novelty acts (Box-folder 16/26)
  - Performing Groups (Box-folder 16/27)
  - Major Bowes (Box-folder 16/28)
  - Ted Mack (Box-folder 16/29)
  - Game shows (Box-folder 16/30)
  - Stage Set (Box-folder 16/31)
  - Promotional banners and billboard (Box-folder 16/32)
  - Others, identified and unidentified (Box-folder 16/33)
- Correspondence (Box-folder 17/1-26)
  Correspondence, drafts, letters received variously related to the operation and performers of the Amateur Hour.
  Arrangement is by subject
  - Drafts and copies of letters of Lou Goldberg, June 26, 1936 to February 11, 1957 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Drafts and copies of letters of Daniel Manjarrez, March 27, 1957 to June 25, 1957 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Drafts and copies of letters sent by Harry McWilliams, June 1, 1936 to December 2, 1957 (Box-folder 17/3-6)
  - Letters received, filed alphabetically by correspondent (Box-folder 17/7-24)
  - Collage of commendatory letters received by Ted Mack (photocopies) (Box-folder 17/25)
  - Undated and unidentified (Box-folder 17/26)
- Advertising/Sponsor Materials (Box-folder 17/27-37)
  Various types of materials created or generated by the Amateur Hour intended to advertise the unique entertainment value for potential investors or broadcasters.
  - General program information, Includes: Individual documents BOX: 17/27 Ted Mack and the Original Amateur Hour, NBC television BOX: 17/28 The Original Amateur Hour, NBC television BOX: 17/29 (Box-folder 17/27-29)
  - Program ratings sheets, Includes: Mexico BOX: 17/30 United States BOX: 17/31 The Amateur Hour Program examination BOX: 17/32 (Box-folder 17/30-32)
  - Station listings sheets, Includes: Mexican and Carribbean area BOX: 17/33 United States BOX: 17/34 (Box-folder 17/33-34)
  - Program listings (Box-folder 17/35)
  - Other TV & Radio program listings (Box-folder 17/36)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 17/37)
- Promotional Materials (Box-folder 18/1-10)
  Various publications, brochures, and packages created by the Amateur Hour in order to promote its unique entertainment value to potential investors or broadcasters.
  Arrangement is by subject or genre.
  - Press release drafts (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Program fact sheets and announcements (Box-folder 18/2)
  - In-house publications (Box-folder 18/3)
  - Original Amateur Hour magazine (Box-folder 18/4)
  - Flyers and proofs (Box-folder 18/5)
  - Newspaper materials (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Posters (Box-folder 18/7-8)
  - Ted Mack (Box-folder 18/9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 18/10)
- Production Materials (Box-folder 18/11-18)
  Various materials created by the Amateur Hour intended and used for show production.
  - Scripts, Includes: Original Amateur Hour BOX: 18/11 La Hora Internacional Del Aficionado, 9 Mar 1957 - 13 July 1957 BOX: 18/12-13 (Box-folder 18/11-13)
  - Commercials scripts (English and Spanish) (Box-folder 18/14-15)
  - Program order and sequence, La Hora Stage directions (Box-folder 18/16)
  - Stage directions (Box-folder 18/17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 18/18)
- Financial Papers (Box-folder 19/1-10)
  Finacial papers concerning the operation and expenses of the Amateur Hour.
  Arrangement is by subject or genre
  - Balance sheets (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Bank deposits lists (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Bills (facturas) (Box-folder 19/3)
  - Payroll sheets (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Program budgets (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Time/rate tables, Includes: American TV stations BOX: 19/6 Mexican TV stations BOX: 19/7 Mexican radio stations BOX: 19/8 (Box-folder 19/6-8)
  - Travel expenses (Box-folder 19/9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 19/10)
- Legal Papers (Box-folder 19/12-13)
  Contracts and other legal writ concerning the operation and rights acquired by the Amateur Hour.
  Arragnement is by genre or subject
  - Contract for La Hora Internacional (Box-folder 19/12)
  - Servicio Postal Mexicano registration form (Box-folder 19/13)
- Printed Programs of Performances, 1934-1954, undated (Box-folder 19/14)
  Amateur Hour programs from various productions throughout its history.
  Arrangement is chronological by date
  - Printed programs of performances of the Amateur Hour contestants, 1934-1954, undated (Box-folder 19/14)
- Clippings, 1935-1957 (Box-folder 19/15-20/5)
  Clippings from various periodicals related to the Amateur Hour.
  - January 1935 to November 29, 1935 (Box-folder 19/15)
  - January 28, 1936 to December 4, 1936 (Box-folder 19/16)
  - March 11, 1937 to April 20, 1937 (Box-folder 19/17)
  - January 6, 1939 to October 2, 1941 (Box-folder 19/18)
  - August 6, 1947 to May 15, 1953 (Box-folder 19/19)
  - April 19, 1956 to December 5, 1956 (Box-folder 19/20)
  - January 25, 1957 to March 16, 1957 (Box-folder 20/1)
  - April 7, 1957 to June 19, 1957 (Box-folder 20/2)
  - July 1, 1957 to November 6, 1957 (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Collage of clippings (photocopy) (Box-folder 20/4)
  - Undated (Box-folder 20/5)
- Awards (Box-folder 20/6)
  Honorary certificate given to Ted Mack and the Amateur Hour.
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States presented to Ted Mack and The Original Amateur Hour, 2 May 1953. [photocopy] (Box-folder 20/6)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 20/7-20/13)
  Miscellaneous materials related to the Amateur Hour.
  Arrangement is by format or subject
  - Notebook of Lloyd Marx (Box-folder 20/7)
  - Catalogues of films (Box-folder 20/8)
  - Harry McWilliams: Notes from Amateur Hour tours and miscellaneous notes (Box-folder 20/9)
  - Articles (Box-folder 20/10-11)
  - Samples of stationery and forms (Box-folder 20/12)
  - Travel brochures, postcards and maps (Box-folder 20/13)